<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning the qualifications of prayer By J. Buerdsell, M.A. late fellow of Brase-nose College. Oxon.</title>
            <author>Buerdsell, James, 1669 or 70-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77764</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5362C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229486</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899223</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899223</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152584</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77764)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152584)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2306:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning the qualifications of prayer By J. Buerdsell, M.A. late fellow of Brase-nose College. Oxon.</title>
                  <author>Buerdsell, James, 1669 or 70-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The third edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for J. Smith, on London-Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1700?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152584:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning the Qualifications OF <hi>PRAYER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>J. B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERDSELL,</hi> M. A. late Fellow of <hi>Braſe-noſe</hi> College. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Third Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Smith,</hi> on <hi>London-Bridge.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152584:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Diſcourſe concerning the <hi>Qualifications</hi> of <hi>Prayer.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Epheſ. Chap. VI. ver. 18.</hi>
                  </bibl> Praying always with all Prayer and Suplication in the Spirit.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS Religion is the Life of the Soul, ſo is Prayer the vital Spirit of Religion, without which it can neither <hi>live</hi> nor <hi>move,</hi> nor <hi>have its Being.</hi> This is the chief Branch of the worſhip of God, <hi>requir'd</hi> of all who acknowledge Him to be, and moſt reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for all who own the World to be govern'd by his Providence, and themſelves to ſtand in need either of his Grace or his Pardon, or who hope for his <hi>Rewards,</hi> or fear his Puniſhments in a future State. And as it is thus a very neceſſary Duty, ſo (if exactly practic'd) is it a difficult one too. For it is a Diſcourſing with God; and for Man, <hi>who is but of yeſterday,</hi> to correſpond with the Almighty, <hi>who inhabits Eternity,</hi> muſt emply the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt force of all his powers and Faculties. For if the <hi>Cherubim</hi> and <hi>Seraphim,</hi> who were always without Spot or Blemiſh, and in whom was never found any Guile, cover their Faces while they are Praiſing and Adoring the infinite Perfections of God; what Geſture can be humble enough for Man, who compoſes himſelf to Pray to him laden with his Sins, and whoſe Iniquities have gone over his Head? If thoſe glorious Spirits are deſcrib'd in Scripture, as ſhifting from place to place while they are worſhiping their Creator, as conquer'd and over-power'd by the Purity of his Nature; with what Confuſion muſt Man appear before Him, who was <hi>conceiv'd in Sin and born in Iniquity?</hi> What atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and application of Thought? What modeſty of Expreſſion? What ſubmiſſiveneſs of Behaviour? What Love and Admiration? What warmth of Affection muſt be us'd to make our Sacrifices acceptable to our Maker? And certainly as it had been the higheſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, to have offer'd to have entertain'd any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe with the Almighty, had not He Himſelf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag'd it; ſo ſince he has vouchſafed to do it, it is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152584:2"/> our moſt excellent Glory, that we can addreſs our ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications to Him. But ſtill the Obligation abides, to put them up with all the Devotion and Fervency of Spirit, which our Imperfections are capable of; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelves with the niceſt diligence, that we may <hi>Pray always with all Prayer and Suplication in the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Praying always, is not meant a conſtant or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued exerciſe of the Act of Prayer, ſo as to be alwas invoking the Name of God. For this would be incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with our other relative Duties: For there are Virtues to be practic'd, which more immediately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard our Neighbour and our ſelves, as well as thoſe which ſolely reſpect God; and we are oblieg'd to Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, Charity and Humanity, as well as to Pray, Praiſe and Adore. But by <hi>Praying always,</hi> is to be underſtood ſuch a Godlike Frame and Temper of Spirit, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd with ſuch an Innocence of Life, and reliſh of Heavenly Things, that we may be ever diſpos'd for this Duty, when fit Opportunities ſhall call for it. By <hi>Praying in the Spirit</hi> (whatſoever the <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> pretend) ſeems to be only imply'd, that our Prayers ought to have the <hi>Qualifications</hi> before-mention'd; ſo that they ought to be put up rather for things Spiritual, than Temporal; for God's Aſſiſtance to enable us to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in Goodneſs, for the removal or averting of Temptations, for all Graces needful for us, and Means for the ſecuring or encreaſing of them; which are ſtyl'd the Gifts, or Privileges of the <hi>Holy Spirit:</hi> And this too falls under the former Head, and is a Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation neceſſary to make us Pray aright; ſince <hi>there can</hi> be no better Argument that we are well qualified for Prayer, than that we pray for Bleſſings of the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Importance, the moſt momentous Concern. So that in the Text are couch'd the Qualifications requir'd to make us ſucceſsful Petitioners at the Throne of Grace. For the reaſon why ſo many Prayers are not heard by Heaven, after thoſe Promiſes which are annex'd to the Performance of this Duty, is, becauſe we are not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152584:3"/> duly accompliſh'd to be Candidates for its Mercies. And it is eaſy for us in this Caſe, to vindicate the Faithfulneſs of God, and to make an Apology for our Maker, in our Maker's own Words, which are, that <hi>We ask and receive not, becauſe we ask amiſs.</hi> In <hi>order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> to make us fit Supplicants to the God of Glory, and to put our Souls into ſuch a Temper, that they may be conſtantly and habitually fitted for the Diſcharge of this Duty, there are ſeveral Qualifications needful. I ſhall therefore conſider.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> What Qualifications are neceſſary to prepare us for Prayer, or before we pray, and in order to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> What is requir'd in the very time, or act of our Praying, when our Devotions are on the Wing, and our Lips are <hi>touch'd with a Coal from the Alter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> What muſt be done after we have Pray'd, to make our attecedent Prayers duly effectual.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> What Acts are to be continued and extended through each of theſe, both before, in, and after our Prayers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> therefore, what Qualifications are neceſſary to prepare us for Prayer, or before we Pray, and in order to it.</p>
            <p>Now the Firſt Qualification neceſſary to prepare us for Prayer, is the Purity of our Hearts, or the direction of our Lives by the Commandments of God. For if our Affections are impure, or our ways unrighteous, it is invain to make our Applications to God: For we know that <hi>God heareth not Sinners, but if any Man is a worſhiper of God, and doth his Will, him he heareth. For the Eyes of the Lord are over the Righteous, and his Ears are open to their Prayers alone.</hi> For without Godlineſs, what ſoever <hi>Antinomian</hi> Schemes ſome Perſons may draw, whether it conſiſts in Innocence, or ſincere Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, our Prayers can never mount up to the preſence of God; becauſe the Burden of our Sins will certainly keep them from aſcending to that Holy Place, where nothing but what is compleatly, ſo can appear. And
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152584:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> it would be Preſumption, to hope that our ſpotleſs Saviour ſhould preſent ſo unacceptable a Sacrifice to his Father, as the Petitions of a Supplicant, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares himſelf to be in a ſtate of Hoſtility againſt both of them, by an avow'd complying with what <hi>they moſt</hi> abhor. Nay, it is the moſt unwarrantable Inſolence, for him who ſtill retains a Love for his Sins <hi>and yields</hi> to them upon the general returns of Temptation, to approach his Maker in any Holy Office. For it is only an <hi>honouring Him with his Lips, while his Heart is far from Him;</hi> and ſeems to be what the Apoſtle calls a <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God,</hi> a profeſſing himſelf his <hi>moſt</hi> devoted, moſt obedient Servant, while his own Conſcience, by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection on his Actions, will tell him that he is his <hi>open</hi> and inveterate Enemy. 'Tis a colluding with him, <hi>who tries the Heart and the Reigns, and to whoſe Eyes all things are naked and open:</hi> as if Omniſcience could be <hi>impos'd</hi> on by Pretences, or a Religious Pageantry was tanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to Solid Virtue and Piety; or ſaying of <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> would excuſe for the not doing the Will of <hi>our Father which is in Heaven.</hi> So that tell we are free from all known and wilful Sin, 'tis no purpoſe to <hi>make</hi> any Supplication to God. He will not hear, will not regard our Prayers. They are like <hi>unhallowed Fire</hi> offer'd to Him, and are <hi>an abomination in his ſight;</hi> for of him <hi>who</hi> is not reſolv'd to part with his Sins, the very Prayers are ſinful. That Duty which draws other nigher to God caſt him at a greater diſtance from him. That Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance which ſanctifies others, ſerves only to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate his deplorable State, and to render his Condition more inſufferable. But neither, on the other hand, is he leſs criminal, if he does not Pray at all: For he is not excus'd from this Duty, by being unqualify'd for it, but he becomes guilty, not only of thoſe Sins which are the hindrances of his Devotion, but of that Inabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to Devotion, which they have caus'd; and ſo <hi>hard</hi> are his Circumſtances, that he is likely to ſuffer, not only for making his Duty impoſſible by ſinning, but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152584:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> even for not diſcharging it, while it is thus impoſſible. And this juſtly enough too, becauſe this Impoſſibility was wlfully ſuperinduc'd; an act of his own choice and free election, and for which he has none to blame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides himſelf, and his own wild Paſſions. So that while his Caſe continues thus, he is on all accounts <hi>unquali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd</hi> for Prayer, and yet is guilty <hi>too</hi> if he does not <hi>pray,</hi> till by hearty Repentance he has freed himſelf from his Sins. So indiſpenſibly neceſſary is Purity from Sin, to prepare us for Prayer. But as there are different kind of Sins, ſo is there the greateſt neceſſity that we ſhould be innocent of thoſe Sins, which are <hi>moſt</hi> oppos'd to the Spirit of Prayer; for they are not all of them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually deſtructive of it. But theſe are malice, ill will, or hatred of our Brother. Now as theſe Vices commence two manner of ways, either by Injuring our Brother, <hi>or</hi> by receiving an Injury from him; ſo we may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd in either Caſe to be guilty of them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on all Regards <hi>unqualify'd</hi> for <hi>Prayer, if we do not contribute our utmoſt towards the ſuppreſſing of them. As for Inſtance: If I have injur'd my Brother, and given him any umbrage to hate me, I am in a great meaſure guilty of the Sin, and therefore am unqualify'd for Prayer, if I do not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour a ſpeedy Reconcilement with him. For if my Gift is before the Altar, and I there remember that my Brother has ought againſt me, (any juſt cauſe of complaining that I have injur'd him,) I am oblig'd to leave my Gift before the Altar, and go, and firſt be reconciled to my Brother. So on the other hand, when we are injur'd by our Brother we are guilty of the Malicc, and the Sin lies at our door, and ſo our Prayers become ineffectual, if we expreſs an eager Deſire to revenge our ſelves; if we ſhew an Averſion and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to forgive him; if we neglect his Propoſals of Peace and Accommodation. For how can we expect that God ſhould pardon our Sins of the blackeſt Character, if we will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give our Fellow-ſervant the leaſt Offence? And has not our Bleſſed Lord taught us, that we cannot pray to God to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us our Treſpaſſes, unleſs we forgive them that treſpaſs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152584:4"/> againſt us? And as often as we uſe this ſacred Prayer of our Saviour's, if we do not forgive thoſe who have offended us from the bottom of our Hearts, we deſire that God would not forgive us; that He would remember and revenge our Sins againſt Him, as we purpoſe to revenge thoſe which our Brother has committed againſt us. So that in effect we turn the beſt Prayer, that ever was, into Sin, and uſe the Words of our Saviour, who ſpake as never man ſpake, to our own Damnation. So that Purity from Sin, eſpecially from Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Hatred or Ill-will, is the first</hi> Qualification <hi>in order to prepare us for Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second preparatory</hi> Qulafication <hi>for Prayer, is a Conſideration of the Nature of our own Wants, and of the Manner by which God has promis'd to ſupply them, that we may know what to pray for, and what Method to take to have our Prayers anſwer'd. And in taking an Eſtimate of our own Wants, we are to conſider our ſelves as Creatures whoſe chief Intereſt depends on a future State, whoſe greateſt Neceſſities are thoſe which regard the Soul. As to what concerns this Life, we are to reſign that over to our heavenly Father's good Providence, with a Father, not my Will, but thine be done. But as to ſpiritual Wants, concerning theſe we are to ſue with the greateſt and moſt unconditionate Importunity, and a pious Violence is to be done to Heaven, till we find our ſelves ſucceſsful in what we pray for. But then,</hi> Secondly, <hi>we muſt reflect on the Terms on which God has undertaken to aſſiſt theſe Wants, and to reſolve to comply with them, are they never ſo uneaſy. Thus do we ask for a Pardon for Sins: we know the Terms on which this muſt be granted are, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided we repent and forſake them. We are therefore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to ſet our ſelves about this Repentance and Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before we pray for the Pardon. Thus becauſe Grace and Virtue cannot be compaſt without the uſe of good and wiſe endeavours, we are to reſolve on theſe, before we peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for thoſe. For the Promiſes of God, tho' infallible in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to any Grace, ought nevertheleſs to encourage us to travel with more Ardour and Fidelity, to merit the Effects of them. And if we ask after this manner, it ſhall be given</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152584:5"/> us; for every one who asketh in this wiſe, receiveth.</p>
            <p>The Third Qualification prepatory to Prayer, is Faith or a Truſt in God, that he will grant us what we pray for, according to our Saviour's Promiſe: <hi>All things whatſoever ye ask in Prayer, believing ye ſhall receive.</hi> Now we may be ſaid to be qualify'd with this Grace, when ſenſible of our own Wants, we commend our ſelves to God by Prayer, relying on his Divine Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Power, that he will give us what we ſue for: that is, (as was before hinted) if we are careful of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the Conditions on which he ſtipulated to give; if we ask for Pardon for Sins, in reforming them; for virtuous Endowments, in induſtriouſly <hi>ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> after them; for the Aſſiſtance of God's Spirit, in concurring with it, and making good uſe of it; for Health, or Eaſe, or any other proſperous Turns of Providence and outward things, with a due Submiſſion to God's will, join'd with the uſe of lawful Means to attain them. For to truſt that God will hear us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe, is not Faith, but an unwarrantable Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; not Hope, but preſumption.</p>
            <p>Fourth Qualification preparatory for Prayer, is a good Intention to uſe what God ſhall bleſs us with, to excellent Ends and Deſigns; to the glory of God, and the Advancement of our own, and Brother's Salvation. Otherwiſe, if we only ask for God's Bleſſings, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them on our Luſts, we petition Heaven to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to our Undoing, and beg of the <hi>Almighty mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials</hi> for our Sins, and for Occaſions to provoke him. God is oblig'd to deny us out of Love and Compaſſion; for ſhould he hear us, it would be the greateſt Indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that he is diſpleas'd with us, and that he is <hi>about</hi> to ruin us by ſo cruel an Indulgence.</p>
            <p>So that Freedom from Sin, either by Innocence, or ſincere Repentance, eſpecially from Malice or Ill-will; a Reſolution to perform the Terms, on which Succeſs is promis'd to our Prayers; a Truſt that God will grant us what we thus ask for; and a Good Intention
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152584:5"/> to uſe what God bleſſes our Prayers with to his Glory, <hi>are</hi> Qualifications <hi>antecedently neceſſary to Prayer, and preparatory for it. Without theſe, an Addreſs to the Throne of Grace, is to no purpoſe. The moſt artful and elaborate Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition can meet with no welcome there; but like the Dove, when ſhe was firſt ſent out of the Ark, after it has in vain roam'd about the Heavens, without finding any admiſſion, muſt return to its diſappointed owner empty. And if theſe</hi> Qualifications <hi>are needful for us before we apply our ſelves to God in Prayer, while we are yet at a diſtance from him, what will be ſufficient for us to do in the time and act of Praying, when we are before the very Preſence of the living God, and the pure Eyes of the Eternal are fixt upon us? how dreadful muſt that place be, which by God's being more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately reſident in it, is none other but ſhe Houſe of God, and the Gate of Heaven? ſo that we ſhall enquire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>What is required in the very time and act of our Praying, while our Devotions are on the Wing, and our Lips are touch'd with a Coal from the Altar. Now the firſt</hi> Qualification, <hi>neceſſary for us in the time of Prayer, is Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; becauſe Prayer is a talking with God. And this Humility ought to be form'd in as, Firſt, by the Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Majeſty of that God, with whom we have to do: That He is the higheſt far above all, who has Heaven for his Throne, and the Earth for his Foot-ſtool. Who meaſures the Sea in the palm of his Hands, In whoſe Hand is the Soul of every living thing, and the Breath of all Mankind. Hell is naked before him, and Deſtruction hath no covering. He ſtreicheth out the North over the empty place, and hangeth the Earth upon nothing. And, Secondly, this Humility ought to be rais'd by the ſenſe of our own Vileneſs. Firſt, as we are Men and the Creatures of God, over whom he has an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Power and Authority. As we are nothing but a little breathing Duſt and Aſhes, which after a ſhort time, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry full of trouble, muſt return to that out of which we were form'd. If the moſt glorious of his Creatures are ſo deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before Him, that he puts no truſt in his Servants, and charges even his Angels with Folly; how ſhall they come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152584:6"/> Him, who dwell in Houſes of Clay, whoſe Foundation is in the Duſt? But, Secondly, much more ought we to be humble in our Prayers, as we are Sinners, and worthy (if God ſhou'd reward as after our Sins) of Eternal Death. We have affronted Infinite Majeſty, and therefore deſerve Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Puniſhment.</hi> And tho' through the Mercies of God, and the Merrits of our Bleſſed Saviour, our ſevere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance may hinder the execution of this Sentance; yet we muſt remember, that Humility is a part even of Repentance it ſelf. And the conſideration that it is the Goodneſs of God alone, which makes our Miſery leſs, ought to make our Sin greater, and heighten our Humility for having offended ſo gracious a Creator, when we pray for Remiſſion for thoſe Offences.</p>
            <p>The Second Qualification, in the time of Praying, is a due fixedneſs and attention of Mind. For God is an Object ſo noble, that he demands the utmoſt Intenſion of our Thoughts. They ought all to be collected, and fix'd on him, directed as the <hi>Faces of the Cherubim in the Ark wholly towards the Mercy-ſeat. And</hi> in order to this our Minds ought to be diſengag'd from whatſoever may occaſion their ſtragling; as from an overviolent love of the World, its pleaſures and intereſts, and to be poſſeſt with whatſoever may raiſe a juſt <hi>Attention;</hi> as with an awful ſenſe of the Dignity and Excellence of this Duty, the ineſtimable worth of thoſe Mercies for which we petition, the greatneſs of our wants and neceſſities. Nor is it enough, (as the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> looſely determin in this matter,) that this <hi>Attention</hi> is purpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and intended, tho' it is not executed. Nor is it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, that we come with a Reſolution to be atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, if we do not vigorouſly practice it. For is a Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution a competent Diſcharge of any other Duty? Or was the Son in the Goſpel Juſtify'd for reſolving to go and work in the Vineyard, and yet not doing it? <hi>A</hi> Reſolution to pray in general, might as well abſolve us from not praying at all, as a Reſolution to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive, from not being ſo. Not: tho' God will make
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152584:6"/> abatement for the Imperfection of our <hi>Attention,</hi> reſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the unavoidable weakneſs of our Natures, or our being diſus'd to think or reflect; yet will not he diſpence with the total want of it. <hi>And</hi> if we are ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for this Imperfection of our <hi>Attention,</hi> and endeav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our effectively to correct it, God will concurr with us, and by drawing nigher to us, and diſcovering his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections with a greater luſtre, will make our <hi>Attention</hi> not only eaſy and natural, but even alſo pleaſant and delightful. The Third Qualification of Prayer, in the act of Praying, is a good meaſure of deſire, and ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of affection. For a lukewarm Petitioner beſpeaks a denial, and he himſelf contributes to his own repulſe. He ſeems unconcern'd in making his Suit, and ſo leſs expect God to be leſs concern'd to grant it. He ſeems to ſlight the Mercy, while he asks it. Can it therefore be imagin'd, that he ſhould think himſelf much oblig'd by it, or be thankful for it? while a fervent Prayer ſhews how ardently we deſire a Mercy, and how thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully we are like to receive it. <hi>And</hi> this is a ſtrong In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement for God to beſtow it on us; for He is ſo tender and indulgent, that He cannot deny us any thing which is fit for us, when he ſees us wrought up to a due Valuation of it, and our Hearts earneſtly bent upon it. <hi>For it is the fervent Prayer of the righteous man, which prevaileth much.</hi> The Fourth Qualification of Prayer, in the act of Praying, is a general love for Mankind, and a concern for their happineſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For the compaſs of our Prayers ought to be as Iarge as that of our Charity, and with its open <hi>Arms</hi> embrace all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: extended even to thoſe, who are perhaps con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving to lay our <hi>Honours and Bodies in the Duſt, while</hi> we are mounting their Souls, in our Devotions, up to the Heavens. For we are oblig'd by our Holy Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>to bleſs them which curſe us, and to pray for them which deſpitefully uſe us. And</hi> in perſuit of this univerſal Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, our Saviour, (according to St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s pious Obſervation,) has taught us to ſay, <hi>Our,</hi> and not <hi>My
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152584:7"/> Father,</hi> only, <hi>which art in Heaven,</hi> that mindful of our divine and common Original, and of that glorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on which we ſtand related to God, we might unite our Prayers for all thoſe, who bear the ſame il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Character of the <hi>Sons of God.</hi> The Fifth Qualification of Prayer is, that our Prayers ought to be ſhort, not abounding with an exceſs of Words. For Prayer is the Language of the Heart, rather than of the Tongue; of the affections, more than of the lips; and great and rais'd Paſſions, ſuch as make up the moſt perfect Devotion, are ſeldom attended with a copious fluency of Words. For the Soul is <hi>too</hi> much employ'd within, to have leiſure to exerciſe it ſelf about Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, or tedious Harangue. Of this conciſe Nature <hi>are</hi> moſt of the ſacred Hymns and Prayers which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, ſuitable to the Majeſty of God: for the moſt ſhort, is alſo the moſt ſolemn and ſtately method of addreſs, and agreeable to Mankind's Infirmities, which hinders us from enlivening, with a due Spirit, a long and tedious <hi>Prayer.</hi> Of this Nature are <hi>our Saviour's</hi> own Prayers; one of the laſt of which, in his Agony, is ſo ſhort, and yet ſo pathetical, that it ſeems (<hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to</hi> the Hiſtory) to be accompany'd with more <hi>drops of Blood</hi> than Words. The Laſt Qualification in the act of praying, is perſeverance, not as the <hi>Meſſallians,</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtle's</hi> Command in the <hi>Words,</hi> of Praying always thought, by an unbroken continuation of the acts of Prayer; but by a conſtant Preparation, <hi>for and</hi> exerciſe of them, as <hi>opportunities,</hi> and freedom from other Duties demand. For this is the perfection, not <hi>only of</hi> Prayer, but <hi>of</hi> all Virtues. Without this they are only faint efforts, and attempts to pleaſe <hi>God,</hi> which ſhall never be accepted of, nor rewarded by Him. But it has a moſt eſpecial force in Prayer: for if the unjuſt Judge in the <hi>Goſpel, who neither fear'd God, nor regarded Man,</hi> yet granted the Widow's Petition, mov'd purely by her reſolute Perſeverance; how much <hi>more</hi> ſhall <hi>God</hi> who is the juſt Judge of all Mankind, and <hi>whoſe Goodneſs</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152584:7"/> inclines him to be kind and beneficent to his Creatures, grant our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, <hi>if we cry day and night to Him?</hi> I tell you, (as the Goſpel has it) <hi>He will grant them ſpeedily. Humillity, therefore Attention, Fervour, Charity and Perſeverance, are Qualifications neceſſary in the time of Prayer.</hi> But there are, <hi>Thirdly, Qualifications,</hi> neceſſary after we have pray'd, to make our antecedent Prayers duly effectual. As Firſt, an obſervation of God's returns to our Prayers; and eyeing the tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his Providence, whether he does grant our Petitions or not; eſpecially as to ſpiritual concerns. And there is an infallible Mark to meaſure our ſucceſs by: for we may aſſuredly conclude, That God has heard our Prayers, as to pardon of ſins, (for inſtance) if we find our ſelves free from voluntary Tranſgreſſions But if after our <hi>prayers</hi> we are as much ſinners as ever, this is a ſign that God has not heard our Petitions, and that our ſins are not pardon'd; and the fault muſt be our own, becauſe we did not truly repent of them, before we pray'd for their Remiſſion. So that we muſt renew our Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as well as our prayers; and if the former is ſincere, and the latter duly qualify'd, we ſhall certainly be ſucceſsful. Thus we may know that God has granted our prayers as to ſpiritual Graces, if we find our ſelves improv'd in Virtue after our prayers: otherwiſe the fault is our own; we have not endeavour'd vigorouſly after Grace. So that we muſt reinforce our Endeavours as well as our prayers; and if there is no deficiency on our part<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is certain there will be none on God's: for <hi>He is always more ready to give, then we to pray.</hi> He is prepar'd to prevent with his Bleſſings even our firſt Wiſhes for them, and to reward our pious deſires, even before they have time to cloath themſelves with words. The ſecond <hi>Qualification</hi> after prayer, is a returning God thanks for his grants and denials: that is, His denials of temporal Advantages For this is often as great a proof of his Fatherly Goodneſs and Concern for us, as any of His moſt merciful Indulgences. 'Tis a Myſterious Method of Kindneſs, which obliges us againſt our Wills, and makes us happy in contradiction to our moſt paſſionate deſires; depriving us of <hi>what</hi> would prove to us only a more agreeable Ruine, a more pleaſant and beautiful deſtruction. And how ſevere ſo ever diſappointments may appear to us at firſt, yet the event and cloſe of Things will ſhew, that we had good reaſon to be thankful to God, for His croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing us in our Wiſhes, and for viſibly fruſtrating us in the ſucceſs of our prayers; and we ſhall at laſt find the ſatisfaction of conſigning our choice over to Omniſcience, and that God, (to uſe our Saviour's familiar but expreſſive Words with ſome alteration) when we pray'd for a Serpent, has given us a Fiſh, and when we petition'd for a Stone, has bleſt us with Bread. The Third <hi>Qualification</hi> after prayer, is a due value of our great Privilege, that we may pray to God. For how great is the Perogative of a Chriſtian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he may diſcourſe, and converſe, and prevail with God? That there is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of Acceſs, no doubt of Acceptation, that <hi>thers</hi> is no hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152584:8"/> of his Entercourſe with the Almighty, but his own Sins which are no longer impediments, but as far as they are perſiſted in, and not broken off by true <hi>Repentance.</hi> The Fourth <hi>Qualification,</hi> is a learning by God's denials to make fitter Addreſſes for <hi>the future<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> for if my prayers are not granted, <hi>there</hi> muſt be ſome fault in me. Till that is <hi>amended, Heaven</hi> will <hi>be</hi> deaf to my Petitions, and <hi>neglect</hi> my moſt ſolemn Addreſs, Either I do not pray for what <hi>I</hi> ought, or not after that manner which <hi>I</hi> ought, <hi>therefore,</hi> in the Language of the Pſalmiſt, my <hi>Words are only like the Chaff before the Wind, and the Angel of the Lord will certainly ſcatter them</hi> The Fifth <hi>Qualification</hi> is Alms-giving For it is <hi>meet</hi> that we ſhould expreſs our gratitude for God's <hi>Mercies,</hi> by bounty to our <hi>Brethren,</hi> which ask of us, and <hi>need</hi> our relief. This is all the return we can make to providence, for the innumerable Bounties which it ſcatters upon us with open hands. This is a kind of <hi>relieving</hi> our Saviour in his ſuffering Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and he tells us, that he will look on it, as if done to himſelf. And <hi>there</hi> can be no greater inducement for God to beſtow tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral good things on us, than if we conſecrate a part of them to him by our Alms We <hi>render</hi> him, if <hi>I</hi> may ſo ſpeak, our Debtor, and (pardon the boldneſs of the Expreſſion) we may, in ſome meaſure, according to the promiſes made to this Duty, appeal to his Juſtice, as well as to his Goodneſs, to make ſuitable Requitals; which he will moſt ceatainly perform, though not in kind, yet in what will be much more for our Advantage; and will conſult, tho' not our preſent ſatisfaction, yet our laſting Benefit. <hi>On Obſervation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of God's returns to our Prayers, Thanksgiving for his Grants and Denials, a due Value of the privilege of Prayer, a correcting our prayers for the future by our paſt diſappointments,</hi> and laſtly <hi>Alms-giving,</hi> are neceſſary after we have pray'd, to make our antecedent Prayers duly effectual. So that <hi>I</hi> ſhall <hi>proceed</hi> to enquire into. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> what Acts are to be continued and <hi>extended</hi> through each of <hi>theſe,</hi> both before in, and after our prayers. And Firſt, we ought to be poſſeſt with a great ſenſe of our <hi>Imperfections,</hi> in the diſcharge of this weighty Duty. This muſt run thro' all the parts of it, but ought more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to be expreſt both <hi>before,</hi> and after our Devotions. At both <hi>theſe</hi> times we ought ſolemnly to <hi>entreat</hi> God's pardon for the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors that we have, or may commit; for the ſtragling of our Thoughts, which the beſt of Men can more eaſily bewail, than pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, ſince the moſt watchful and ſteady Mind cannot hinder all the diſorders of roving Fancy, in the midſt of our moſt ſerious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, for our earneſt begging of Bleſſings of a trival nature, or for our want of any of the former <hi>Qualification,</hi> in that Meaſure which is expedient. The next <hi>Qualification</hi> is a very comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive one, and which takes in all the reſt, and yet withal a very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary one too and that is univerſal Holineſs and Sanctity. For our praying in a ſhort time will make us leave off our Sins, or our Sins our prayers. So that this will be an effect, as well as a Qualification
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152584:8"/> of our Devotion. For tho' the former Qualifications may be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for a new Convert, and for one who has but lately had the ſenſe and conviction of Religion upon his mind; yet from a proficient in this Duty nothing will be accepted leſs than a general, a compleat and uniform Obedience to all God's Commands. For tho' the prayers of one who begins to leave his Sins, and yet ſometimes upon the prevalency of Cuſtom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or the ſurprize of a violent Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, relapſes into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em, may be heard upon his Repentence; yet this ſtate of Sinning and Repenting muſt not continue long. A general piety muſt be ſuperinduc'd or elſe it is a ſign that his prayers have not had their due efficacy: if they do not conquer all ſin, at leaſt ſo that it may not reign in us; if they do not give us ſome ſort of foretaſt of the Joys of that place, to which they are directed, and make our Souls ſympathize and <hi>conform themſelves with the Virtue and Innocence of its bleſſed Inhabitants. So that the ſumm of all is: That Purity, a Conſideration of our Wants, a Truſt in God, a good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention are neceſſary to prepare us for Prayer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Humility, Attention, Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, Charity, Brevity and Perſeverance in the time of praying. On Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of God's providence, a Vaine of our privilege to pray a Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our prayers by our Diſappointments, and Alms-giving are requir'd after we have pray'd. And a ſenſe of our own Imperfections, and an Univerſal piety are to run through all the periods of this Duty. A prayer which is put up to Heaven after this Method, is ſurely more ſuitable for a reaſonable Creature to preſent before his Almighty Maker, than what is utter'd by, or rather impreſs'd upon a Soul, caſt into a purely paſſive ſtate or poſture; into a State of expectation of the Divine Exmanations to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the Mind, as that Duty has been model'd by ſome late Enthuſiaſts. Which is but what had been before advanc'd by Enthuſiaſts of our own Nation: for thus an Author of great Character, amongſt the moſt ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular Sect which ever oppos'd this Church, allows of no uſe of our own Intellectual powers, of our paſſions, Imaginations, or Wills, in the exerciſe of this Duty: Becauſe (ſays he) God will be ſerv'd with his own alone, and not with any thing in Man, which is come in ſince the fail; ſo the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, Thinkings and Conceivings are ſhut out. And theſe Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions before hinted at, ſeem much more intelligible,</hi>
               <q>James Naylor's Love to the Loſt, pag. <hi>13.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>more adapted to the Oeconomy of our Devotion, that the taking hold of eſſential Truth nakedly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as it is in it ſelf; than the applying the Mind to the intelligible World, the World of Truth, than the addreſſing to the Ideal World; than the Union with God, the ſeeing of all things in God: Terms in ſome meaſure invented by two refin'd and curious Thinkers, the one of our own, the other of a Neighbouring Kingdom. And here I cannot but</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>See</hi> Norris<hi>'s Reflections on the Conduct of Hamane life,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Sect</hi> 11. <hi>reflect on a dangerous Error of a Myſtick Writer of note, who ſeems to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude Vertue</hi> from the ſtate of transform'd Souls, (as he ſtyles them) and thoſe wrapt up in the higheſt Tranſports of Devotion. But that Virtue is not only a preparation for Devotion, but alſo a compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152584:9"/> of it, has <hi>been</hi> ſhewn in this Diſcourſe: and not only ſo, but that it is practic'd by the bleſſed, by whom Devotion is exercis'd in its moſt exalted flights, was made out (tho' far below the Majeſty of the Subject,) in another Effay. But to cloſe all: Furniſh'd with the former <hi>Qualifications,</hi> we may be juſtly ſaid to pray always, and in the Spirit. Yet ſuch Prayers as <hi>were</hi> before deſcrib'd, will <hi>never</hi> fail of ſucceſs, till God ſhall ceaſe from being true, and our Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty's ſtrength from being Merciful. Such prayers as <hi>theſe</hi> will <hi>be</hi> acceptable Sacrifices to the Heavenly Altar, will procure pardon for Sin, and Encreaſe of Grace, and at length Eternal Life, and will at laſt <hi>expire</hi> into everlaſting Thanksgiving. When <hi>we</hi> ſhall <hi>need</hi> to pray no more, but this Duty (as ſome fancy of Faith and Hope) ſhall ceaſe, and <hi>we</hi> ſhall have nothing to do for <hi>ever,</hi> but to give Thanks, Adore and Praiſe.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer to be uſed in ſecret.</head>
               <p>O Lord look down from Heaven with an Eye of Favour and <hi>come paſſion</hi> upon me thy poor Creature, who in and through Jeſus Chriſt do look up unto thee for Mercy. I am a Sinner by Nature and by practice, who deſerve to be caſt into everlaſting Fire: But do thou deliver me from all my Sins. Give me thy grace, that I may not harbour any vain or wicked thoughts in my Heart, that I may not lye or ſwear or take thy holy Name in vain, or any other way of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend <hi>thee</hi> with my Tongue ſuffer <hi>me</hi> not to be guilty of ſtealing or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>deceit:</hi> but grant that I may <hi>be</hi> true and faithful and diligent in the place <hi>where</hi> thou art pleaſed to ſet <hi>me:</hi> knowing thine <hi>All ſeeing Eye</hi> obſerves <hi>me</hi> in the moſt <hi>ſecret</hi> Corner, and that my own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is more than a Thouſand Witneſſes Inable <hi>me</hi> to <hi>flee</hi> Youthful Luſts, and to follow after Godlineſs, and ſuffer <hi>me</hi> not to be a Lover of <hi>pleaſures</hi> more than of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> prepare <hi>me</hi> for Death and Judgment: and cauſe <hi>me</hi> ſo to live in thy Fear and favour while I am <hi>here,</hi> that <hi>whenever</hi> it ſhall <hi>pleaſe thee</hi> to remove <hi>me</hi> hence, I may be received into a Manſion in Heaven, and the full Enjoyment of that Glory: which neither Eye hath <hi>ſeen,</hi> nor Ear heard, nor hath <hi>ever entred</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Heart of Man to conceive. Bleſs theſe Nations our King and all that are in Authority. Bleſs all thy Miniſters, all my Friends and Relations, and all thy people. Bleſs this Family and make me a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in it. Comfort thoſe that mourn, and ſuppyly their wants.</p>
               <p>And now <hi>O</hi> Lord, as thou haſt <hi>been</hi> good unto me this Day <hi>(or Night)</hi> paſt, ſo bleſs me this Night, <hi>(or Day)</hi> continue thy Mercies unto my Soul and Body, and give me thy Grace, that i may be truly thankful for them, and careful to make a good uſe of them. Above all i bleſs thy glorious Name for Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Grant that i may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him in a right manner, and for his ſake do thou accept of me and my poor prayers which I conclude, as he himſelf hath taught me to pray unto thee,</hi> Our Father which art in Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>hallowed be thy Name, thy Kingdom come, thy Will be done on Eatth as it is in Heaven, Give us this day our daily Bread, and forgive us our Treſpaſſes as we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us, lead us not into Temptation, but deliver us from Evil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for thine is the Kingdom the power and the Glory for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152584:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152584:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152584:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
